<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Statistical Analysis on Jethro Vanbrook&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://burningsky0306.github.io/categories/statistical-analysis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Statistical Analysis on Jethro Vanbrook&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>BurningSky0306@gmail.com (Fan Jianbo)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>BurningSky0306@gmail.com (Fan Jianbo)</webMaster>
    <copyright>Jethro Vanbrook</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 19:16:57 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://burningsky0306.github.io/categories/statistical-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How to Build and Compare Statistical Models Through Regression Analysis and Significance Testing</title>
      <link>https://burningsky0306.github.io/notes/how-to-build-and-compare-statistical-models-through-regression-analysis-and-significance-testing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 19:16:57 +0800</pubDate><author>BurningSky0306@gmail.com (Fan Jianbo)</author>
      <guid>https://burningsky0306.github.io/notes/how-to-build-and-compare-statistical-models-through-regression-analysis-and-significance-testing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This article systematically examines the fundamentals of linear regression modeling and statistical validation. It introduces the one-variable linear regression framework, emphasizing its construction via least squares optimization to minimize prediction errors (\(SS_{\text{residual}} = \sum{(\hat{y}-y)^2}\)). The analysis highlights significance testing (t-tests for slope parameters, F-tests for model comparisons) and critical metrics like \(R^2\) and adjusted mean squared error (\(MS_{\text{error}}\)) that balance prediction accuracy against model complexity. A key focus is hierarchical regression, demonstrating how covariate-controlled models enhance robustness in identifying meaningful predictors. The discussion further underscores the value of multi-dimensional operational definitions (e.g., physiological/behavioral metrics) for reinforcing result reliability. Practical guidelines for interpreting degrees of freedom, model comparisons, and error decomposition provide actionable insights for empirical research design.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
